Finding Aid for Arthur W. Bromage (1904-1979) Papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur W Bromage papers 1917-1979, 1935-1975
Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.
3 linear feet
8582 Aa 2
Professor of political science at the University of Michigan specializing in municipal government, Ann Arbor, Michigan city council member 1949-1953, member of several state commissions and boards, consultant to numerous city charter commissions. Papers relate primarily to his service on Ann Arbor city council and his research interests.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 2858 8329 ) was transferred in two separate accessions. The first transfer was from Mary C. Bromage in 1979. The second transfer was from Susanna Bromage Paterson in 1995.
The collection is open for research.
Arthur Watson Bromage was born in East Windsor, Connecticut on February 27, 1904. He attended Enfield High School in Connecticut from 1917 to 1921. His undergraduate education took place at Wesleyan University in Connecticut from 1921 to 1925. He received his Master's degree from Harvard University in 1926 and his Ph.D. in 1928.
As a specialist in municipal government and administration, Arthur Bromage was associated with the University of Michigan beginning in 1929. He attained the rank of professor of political science in 1938, and served as chairman of the department from 1961 to 1964. He attained the status of professor emeritus in 1974. Long active in the university's Institute of Public Administration, Professor Bromage participated in training graduate students for careers in city management.
During World War II, Bromage was commissioned in January 1943 as a major in the Army. Bromage attended the School of Military Government in Charlottesville, Virginia. Afterward he was assigned to Fort Custer in Michigan from May 1943 to January 1944. He served overseas in England, France and Germany from February 1944 to September 1945. As a Lieutenant Colonel, he served with the Regional Military Government Detachment for Bavaria in 1945, participating in the restoration of civil authority in that region of Germany. He was awarded the European, Africa, Middle East ribbon with three battle stars, the American campaign medal and the World War II victory medal. After World War II, he resumed his position as professor of political science at the University of Michigan.
In addition to university teaching and research, Bromage served as a city councilman in Ann Arbor from 1949 until 1953. Throughout his career, he was active in the National Municipal League. He served, by appointment of the governors of Michigan, on four state and local study commissions. He contributed to city, county and citizen bodies as secretary to the Michigan Commission of Reform and Modernization of Government in 1938 and as a member of the Michigan Commission on Intergovernmental Relations from 1954 until 1955. In 1956, Bromage was given an honorary life member status in the International City Manager's Association and of the Michigan Municipal League. He was a charter consultant to numerous cities.
Among Bromage's publications are many books, articles and notes on state, municipal, county and metropolitan government. His best known works include:
American County Government,
Organization and Cost of County and Township Government,
State Government and Administration in the U.S.,
Manager Plan Abandonments,
Introduction to Municipal Government and Administration,
On the City Council,
A Councilman Speaks,
and
Councilmen at Work.
His syndicated articles, released through the National League of Cities, appeared in state municipal league journals throughout the United States.
He was a member of: American Political Science Association, American Society for Public Administration, International City Managers' Association, and National Municipal League. In 1973, the Michigan Chapter of the International City Managers' Association established the Arthur W. Bromage Internship, a graduate internship, annually awarded at the University of Michigan.
He and Mary Cogan were married in 1928. They had one daughter, Susanna Bromage Paterson, six grandchildren and twelve great grandchildren. Arthur Bromage died on February 9, 1979 in his home in Ann Arbor.
The Arthur Bromage papers are divided into five series:
Correspondence, 1936-1979 (0.2 linear ft.)
Speeches, 1942-1971 (0.3 linear ft.)
Topical, 1942-1971 (0.5 linear ft.)
Press Clippings, 1928-1972 (5 bound volumes and 5 folders)
Writings, 1924-1979 (0.3 linear ft.)
The Arthur Bromage papers provide documentation of his service as Ann Arbor city councilman and other political activities and some of his academic research. The papers include correspondence, speeches, press clipping s and publications.
Subjects:
Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.; Bavaria (Germany)--Politics and government--1945-; Municipal government.; Germany.
- Correspondence 1936-1979, 0.2 linear feet
  The Correspondence series is organized chronologically and includes only professional correspondence. His correspondence with his wife is included in the Mary C. Bromage papers, also housed at the Bentley Historical Library.
  - 1936-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
- Speeches 1942-1971, 0.3 linear feet
  The Speeches series is organized chronologically. Included are speeches Arthur Bromage gave as an Ann Arbor councilman and in other political forums.
  - 1942-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1952-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - 1970-1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Topical 1942-1971, 0.5 linear feet
  The Topical series is organized alphabetically. Included under the heading "Military Experience" are Arthur Bromage's service records and other materials documenting his experience with military government overseas during World War II. The rest of the material in the Topical series is from other events or activities in which Bromage participated.
  - Ann Arbor Alderman 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1)
  - Biography (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews, 1931-1971 (Box 1)
  - Bromage Fellowship, 1977-1993 (Box 1)
  - Class Material (University of Michigan) 1951, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Committee Papers 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Creelman Estate 1969 (Box 1)
  - Diary of England and France, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Education, 1917-1925 (Box 1)
  - Military Experience
    - General School Reports 1943 (Box 1)
    - Military Government, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Service Records, 1942-1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - World War II Writings 1945 (Box 1)
  - Recognition in the Press 1979 (Box 1)
  - Summary of Ph.D. Thesis, 1928 (Box 1)
  - University Activities
    - Harvard College, 1926-1928 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan, 1926-1977 (Box 1)
- Press Clippings 1928-1972, 5 folders; 5 bound volumes
  The Press Clippings series includes clippings from newspapers where either Arthur Bromage or Mary Bromage are the subject of the article. This series is organized chronologically.
  - 1928-1935 (Box 2)
  - 1937-1954 (Box 2)
  - 1938-1945 (Box 2)
  - 1944-1956 (Box 2)
  - 1945-1952 (Box 2)
  - 1958-1977 (Box 3)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - 1965-1972 (Box 3)
- Writings 1924-1979, 0.3 linear feet
  The Writings series includes various non-published material, Bromage's collegiate papers and thesis, and a selection of his journal publications. Only articles and reprints that were not listed in his bibliography (see Topical Files) were retained for this collection.
  - Ann Arbor City Elections 1964 (Box 3)
  - Cities and villages undated (Box 3)
  - College papers, 1924 (Box 3)
  - College Thesis 1925 (Box 3)
  - County Home Rule, 1962-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Government Activities 1950-1977 (Box 3)
  - Governor's Special Commission on Local Government, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - How to Study Your State Constitution, undated (Box 3)
  - Illinois Home Rule 1964-1966 (Box 3)
  - Model State Constitution, undated (Box 3)
  - Poetry, "The University" 1979 (Box 3)
  - Recollections of Early Years in Warehouse Point 1933 (Box 3)
  - Published articles and reprints of articles (selection) (Box 3)